<refentry id="pickdns">

<refmeta xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<refentrytitle>pickdns</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class="manual">user commands</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="source">djbwares</refmiscinfo>
<xi:include href="version.xml" />
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
<refname>pickdns</refname>
<refpurpose>an obsolete special-purpose content DNS server using the UDP protocol</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
<cmdsynopsis>
<command>pickdns</command>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsection>
<title>Warning</title>

<para>
<command>pickdns</command> is obsolete.
Its functionality was rolled into <citerefentry><refentrytitle>tinydns</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> in 2001.
</para>

</refsection>

<refsection>
<title>Description</title>

<para>
<command>pickdns</command> is a content DNS server that speaks the DNS/UDP protocol.
It accepts DNS queries from hosts around the Internet, and responds with locally configured information.
</para>

<para>
When it starts <command>pickdns</command> changes its root to the directory specified by the <envar>ROOT</envar> environment variable, and drops privileges to run as the user ID and group ID specified by the <envar>UID</envar> and <envar>GID</envar> environment variables.
The latter can be set up with <citerefentry><refentrytitle>envuidgid</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>.
</para>

<para>
Normally <command>pickdns</command> is run via a server program such as <command>udp-socket-listen</command> to listen for DNS/UDP queries from hosts around the Internet.
It understands the <envar>LISTEN_PID</envar> and <envar>LISTEN_FDS</envar> environment variable convention for having an already-listening socket passed to it by such a program, and uses the last open file descriptor in the list that refers to a UDP/IPv4 socket.
If no such open file descriptor is provided it falls back to opening its own UDP/IPv4 socket, bound to port 53 of the IP address given by the value of the <envar>IP</envar> environment variable. 
It does not handle DNS/TCP.
</para>

<para>
<command>pickdns</command> rejects zone-transfer requests, inverse queries, non-Internet-class queries, truncated packets, and packets that contain anything other than a single query.
</para>

<para>
<command>pickdns</command> answers queries as specified by <filename>data.cdb</filename>, a binary file in its root directory created by <citerefentry><refentrytitle>pickdns-data</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>.
It only answers A and AAAA queries.
It finds all of the A or AAAA resource records in the database for the relevant domain name, orders them in a random order, and returns up to the first 3 of them in the response.
All resource records are given a 5 second TTL.
</para>

</refsection>

<refsection>
<title>History</title>
<para>
<command>pickdns</command> was originally part of <personname><firstname>Daniel</firstname><othername>J.</othername><surname>Bernstein</surname></personname>'s djbdns toolset in 2000.
</para>
</refsection>

<refsection>
<title>Author</title>
<para>
Original code and documentation by <personname><firstname>Daniel</firstname><othername>J.</othername><surname>Bernstein</surname></personname>.
Documentation modernizations by <personname><firstname>Jonathan</firstname><surname>de Boyne Pollard</surname></personname>.
</para>
</refsection>

</refentry>
