<refentry id="rblsmtpd">

<refmeta xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<refentrytitle>rblsmtpd</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class="manual">user commands</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="source">djbwares</refmiscinfo>
<xi:include href="version.xml" />
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
<refname>rblsmtpd</refname>
<refpurpose>UCSPI-TCP SMTP server wrapper that blocks mail from RBL-listed sites.</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
<cmdsynopsis>
<command>rblsmtpd</command>
<arg choice='req'><replaceable>opts</replaceable></arg>
<arg choice='req'><replaceable>prog</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsection>
<title>Description</title>

<para>
<command>rblsmtpd</command> normally just chains to <replaceable>prog</replaceable>, which is the command name and arguments of a UCSPI-TCP server program that is expected to carry out an SMTP conversation to receive incoming mail messages. 
</para>

<para>
However, <command>rblsmtpd</command> does not invoke <replaceable>prog</replaceable>
if it is told to block mail from this client. 
Instead it carries out its own limited SMTP conversation, rejecting all attempts to send a message with a temporary or a permanent failure response.
Meanwhile it prints one line on its standard error to log its activity.
</para>

<para>
It drops the limited SMTP conversation after 60 seconds, even if the client has not quit by then.
</para>

<refsection>
<title>Blocked clients</title>

<para>
Whether clients are blocked is determined by environment variables.
Normally <command>rblsmtpd</command> runs under <citerefentry><refentrytitle>tcpserver</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>; you can use <citerefentry><refentrytitle>tcprules</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> to set <envar>RBLSMTPD</envar> for selected clients. 
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>tcpserver</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry> also sets up <envar>TCPREMOTEIP</envar> as the IP address of the remote host.
</para>

<para>
If the <envar>RBLSMTPD</envar> environment variable is set and is nonempty, <command>rblsmtpd</command> blocks mail. 
It uses <envar>RBLSMTPD</envar> as an error message to send to the client. 
</para>

<para>
If <envar>RBLSMTPD</envar> is set and is empty, <command>rblsmtpd</command> does not block mail. 
</para>

<para>
If <envar>RBLSMTPD</envar> is not set, <command>rblsmtpd</command> looks up <envar>TCPREMOTEIP</envar> in the RBL, and blocks mail if <envar>TCPREMOTEIP</envar> is blacklisted.
</para>

<para>
You may supply any number of <arg choice='plain'>-r</arg> and <arg choice='plain'>-a</arg> options to control RBL lookup.
<command>rblsmtpd</command> tries each list in turn until it finds one that blacklists or whitelists <envar>TCPREMOTEIP</envar>.
</para>

<para>
Prior versions of <command>rblsmtpd</command> would default to using the RBL source <filename>rbl.maps.vix.com</filename> if you did not supply any blacklists.
<ulink url="http://dnsbl.com/2007/02/status-of-rblmapsvixcom-invalid-domain.html">This list has been defunct for many years and is no longer a built-in default in this program</ulink>.
Learning from this experience, there is no replacement built-in default; no blacklists supplied means no blacklisting done.
</para>

<para>
If you want to run your own RBL blacklist or whitelist for <command>rblsmtpd</command>, you can use <citerefentry><refentrytitle>rbldns</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>.
</para>

</refsection>

<refsection>
<title>Temporary or permanent failure responses</title>

<para>
Normally, if <envar>RBLSMTPD</envar> is set, <command>rblsmtpd</command> uses a 451 error code in its limited SMTP conversation. 
This tells legitimate clients to try again later. 
It gives innocent relay operators a chance to see the problem, prohibit relaying, get off the RBL, and get the mail delivered. 
</para>

<para>
However, if the value of <envar>RBLSMTPD</envar> begins with a hyphen, <command>rblsmtpd</command> removes the hyphen and uses a 553 error code.
This tells legitimate clients to bounce the message immediately. 
</para>

<para>
Command line options further alter this behaviour.
</para>

</refsection>

</refsection>

<refsection>
<title>Options</title>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><arg choice='plain'>-r <replaceable>base</replaceable></arg></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Use <replaceable>base</replaceable> as an RBL source, a blacklist.
An IP address <filename>a.b.c.d</filename> is listed by that source if the domain name <filename>d.c.b.a.<replaceable>base</replaceable></filename> has a TXT record in the Domain Name System.
<command>rblsmtpd</command> uses the contents of the TXT record as an error message to send to the client.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><arg choice='plain'>-a <replaceable>base</replaceable></arg></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Use <replaceable>base</replaceable> as an anti-RBL source, a whitelist.
An IP address <filename>a.b.c.d</filename> is listed by that source if the domain name <filename>d.c.b.a.<replaceable>base</replaceable></filename> has an A record in the Domain Name System.
<command>rblsmtpd</command> does not block mail for whitelisted IP addresses.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><arg choice='plain'>-B</arg></term>
<listitem>
<para>
(Default.)
Use a 451 error code for IP addresses blacklisted in the RBL.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><arg choice='plain'>-b</arg></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Use a 553 error code for IP addresses blacklisted in the RBL.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><arg choice='plain'>-C</arg></term>
<listitem>
<para>
(Default.)
Handle RBL lookups in a "fail-open" mode. 
If an RBL blacklist lookup fails temporarily, assume that the address is not listed; if an RBL whitelist lookup fails temporarily, assume that the address is listed. 
Unfortunately, a knowledgeable attacker can force an RBL lookup to fail temporarily, so that his mail is not blocked.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><arg choice='plain'>-c</arg></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Handle RBL lookups in a "fail-closed" mode. 
If an RBL blacklist lookup fails temporarily, assume that the address is listed (but use a 451 error code even with <arg choice='plain'>-b</arg>). 
If an RBL whitelist lookup fails temporarily, assume that the address is not listed (but use a 451 error code even if a subsequent RBL blacklist lookup succeeds and <arg choice='plain'>-b</arg> is used). 
Unfortunately, this sometimes delays legitimate mail.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</refsection>

<refsection>
<title>History</title>
<para>
<command>rblsmtpd</command> was originally part of <personname><firstname>Daniel</firstname><othername>J.</othername><surname>Bernstein</surname></personname>'s ucspi-tcp toolset in 1999.
</para>
</refsection>

<refsection>
<title>Author</title>
<para>
Original code and documentation by <personname><firstname>Daniel</firstname><othername>J.</othername><surname>Bernstein</surname></personname>.
Documentation modernizations by <personname><firstname>Jonathan</firstname><surname>de Boyne Pollard</surname></personname>.
</para>
</refsection>

</refentry>
