<refentry id="tinydns-edit">

<refmeta xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<refentrytitle>tinydns-edit</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class="manual">user commands</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="source">djbwares</refmiscinfo>
<xi:include href="version.xml" />
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
<refname>tinydns-edit</refname>
<refpurpose>edit the source data file used by a content DNS server</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
<cmdsynopsis>
<command>tinydns-edit</command>
<arg choice='req'><replaceable>data</replaceable></arg>
<arg choice='req'><replaceable>tmp</replaceable></arg>
<arg choice='req'>add</arg>
<arg choice='req'><replaceable>type</replaceable></arg>
<arg choice='req'><replaceable>name</replaceable></arg>
<arg choice='req'><replaceable>addr</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsection>
<title>Description</title>

<para>
<command>tinydns-edit</command> atomically modifies a database source file, the input compiled by <citerefentry><refentrytitle>tinydns-data</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>, with the given modification.
It reads the data file <replaceable>data</replaceable>, modifies it,
and writes it to <replaceable>tmp</replaceable>.
Then it atomically renames <replaceable>tmp</replaceable> to <replaceable>data</replaceable>.
The two files must, of course, reside on the same volume in order that this can be achieved.
</para>

<para>
On success, <command>tinydns-edit</command> returns zero.
If, for any reason, an error occurs it will exit with a non-zero code and <replaceable>data</replaceable> will not be changed.
</para>

<para>
The <arg choice='plain'>add</arg> verb is the only supported verb in this version.
In response to it, <command>tinydns-edit</command> adds a record to the database for fully-qualified domain name <replaceable>name</replaceable> of type <replaceable>type</replaceable> with IP address <replaceable>addr</replaceable>.
</para>

<para>
<replaceable>type</replaceable> can be one of 
<variablelist>

<varlistentry>
<term><code>ns</code></term>
<listitem>
<para>
A <code>.</code> record is created to describe a content DNS server. 
This record specifies that the domain <replaceable>name</replaceable> is published by a DNS content server that is listening on the IP address <replaceable>addr</replaceable>.
The name of the DNS content server is not directly specifiable. 
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><code>childns</code></term>
<listitem>
<para>
A <code>&#x0026;</code> record is created describing a delegation. 
This record specifies that queries for names in the domain <replaceable>name</replaceable> should be referred to a ("child") DNS content server that is listening on the IP address <replaceable>addr</replaceable>.
The name of the DNS content server is not directly specifiable. 
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><code>mx</code></term>
<listitem>
<para>
A <code>@</code> record is created describing a mail exchanger. 
This record specifies that mail to names in the domain <replaceable>name</replaceable> should be sent to an SMTP server that is listening on the IP address <replaceable>addr</replaceable>.
The name of the SMTP server is not directly specifiable. 
</para>

<para>
It is not possible to specify the distance value for the SMTP server. 
<command>tinydns-edit</command> will leave that field blank, meaning that tinydns-data (8) will use whatever the default value is.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><code>host</code></term>
<listitem>
<para>
A <code>=</code> record is created describing a bidirectional name to address mapping. 
This record specifies that the name <replaceable>name</replaceable> maps to the IP address <replaceable>addr</replaceable> and vice versa.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><code>alias</code></term>
<listitem>
<para>
A <code>+</code> record is created describing a unidirectional name to address mapping. 
This record specifies that the name <replaceable>name</replaceable> maps to the IP address <replaceable>addr</replaceable>address but that there is no reverse mapping.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>
</para>

<para>
Intermediate domain names are assigned by <command>tinydns-edit</command> itself.
For <code>ns</code> and <code>childns</code> records there is an intermediate domain name of the form <filename><replaceable>a</replaceable>.ns.<replaceable>name</replaceable></filename>.
For <code>mx</code> records there is an intermediate domain name of the form <filename><replaceable>a</replaceable>.mx.<replaceable>name</replaceable></filename>.
<replaceable>a</replaceable> is a letter from "a" to "z".
<command>tinydns-edit</command> checks existing records of the same pattern and for the record being added picks the first available unused letter.
It aborts if there are no letters left.
</para>

<para>
For <code>host</code> records it aborts if there is already a <code>=</code> record that has either <replaceable>name</replaceable> or <replaceable>addr</replaceable>.
By the nature of <code>alias</code> records, <command>tinydns-edit</command> will not abort if there happen to already be existing records that use <replaceable>addr</replaceable>.
</para>

<para>
If any existing <code>ns</code>, <code>childns</code>, and <code>mx</code> records are found when adding that type, it copies their TTL for the record being added.
Otherwise, where no existing records exist and for other types of records, a fixed default TTL is used.
This is 1 day for all records, except for <code>ns</code> and <code>childns</code> records for which it is 3 days.
</para>

</refsection>

<refsection>
<title>History</title>
<para>
<command>tinydns-edit</command> was originally part of <personname><firstname>Daniel</firstname><othername>J.</othername><surname>Bernstein</surname></personname>'s djbdns toolset in 2000.
This manual page was written on 2001-04-06, and revised in 2001-04-26, and again in 2017.
</para>
</refsection>

<refsection>
<title>Author</title>
<para>
Original code by <personname><firstname>Daniel</firstname><othername>J.</othername><surname>Bernstein</surname></personname>.
Documentation by <personname><firstname>Jonathan</firstname><surname>de Boyne Pollard</surname></personname>.
</para>
</refsection>

</refentry>
